<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The suppressing of the assembly of the pretended shee-Iesuites. By the edict of our most holy father and lord, Vrbanus, Dei gratia. The eight (of that name) now Pope of Rome. Translated out of the Low-dutch coppie, printed at Bruxells</title>
            <author>Urban VIII, Pope, 1568-1644.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24524</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102047</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837848</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837848</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2195</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14208)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2195)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1041:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The suppressing of the assembly of the pretended shee-Iesuites. By the edict of our most holy father and lord, Vrbanus, Dei gratia. The eight (of that name) now Pope of Rome. Translated out of the Low-dutch coppie, printed at Bruxells</title>
                  <author>Urban VIII, Pope, 1568-1644.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Dawson?] for Nathaniell Butter, and Nicholas Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The edict was dated 13 Jan. 1630--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Monastic and religious life of women --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2195:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2195:1"/>
            <p>THE SVPPRESSING OF THE ASSEMBLY OF THE PRETENDED Shee-Ieſuites.</p>
            <p>By the Edict of our moſt holy Father and Lord, VRBANVS, <hi>Dei Gratia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eight (of that name) now <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the <hi>Low-dutch</hi> Coppie, Printed at <hi>Bruxells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathaniell Butter,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Bourne.</hi> 1631.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2195:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2195:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus,</hi> Biſhop, Servant of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, to everlaſting Memory.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Paſtorall care and vigilancy of the <hi>Romiſh Pope</hi> (vnto whom the <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Sabbath,</hi> through the vnſpeakeable providence of the chiefeſt and ſupreameſt Father of the Family, is committed) doth chiefely ayme at this ſcope, that no Labourers ſhall preſumptuouſly intrude themſelues into this <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard</hi> without being lawfully called and elected, who may deſtroy the good ſeed, roote out the well-grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, make weeds to ſpring vp, and mixe evill baſtard branches among the good plants.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding that there hath beene made a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſharpe and ſtrong prohibition, by the Chriſtian Ordinances of the Generall <hi>Lateran Councell,</hi> and the <hi>Councell of Lyons,</hi> that no perſon ſhould dare to aſcribe ſo much power to himſelfe, or take vpon him to bring in innovations in Religion, and that likewiſe by the godly Inſtitutions of our predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of bleſſed Memory, <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22. and <hi>Clemens</hi> the fifth, Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> all aſſemblies of Women, inſtituted by their owne power and authoritie, was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2195:3"/>cleane cut off, and rooted out, and condemned as moſt dangerous and pernicious. Nevertheleſſe, (as wee haue vnderſtood not without great griefe and ſorrow of heart) there are in divers parts of <hi>Italy,</hi> and of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> certaine Women and Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, which haue boldly and preſumptuouſly taken vpon them the name of <hi>Shee-Ieſuites,</hi> without the conſent and approbation of the Holy <hi>Apoſtolicall Chaire.</hi> Theſe haue of late yeares made Convents and Aſſemblies, vnder pretence, and ſhew, of leading a devout and religious life. They haue vſed a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar kinde of habit, differing from all other, built E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difices and Houſes in manner of Colledges, erected places named by the name of <hi>Novitiate,</hi> or tryall and probation. In theſe builded Colledges they haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed one to be Generall, and governo over the whole Aſſembly, giving them Stiles of <hi>Shee-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voſts;</hi> Aſcribing and taking vpon them ſuch power and authoritie, as ſeemed good vnto themſelues. Making Vowes and Proteſtations of Povertie, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie, and Obedience, and theſe to ſtand for ſound and ſolemne Vowes, having no ground nor warrant for this their Obedience, but onely their owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and well ſeeming, (all vnder this Cloake and pretence of promoting Soules ſalvation) taking vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them (not withſtanding their Vow) to walke free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly about the Streets, and to performe ſuch workes and buſineſſes, which goe beyond the weakeneſſe, and capacitie, and braine of that ſexe. And which doe in no wiſe beſeeme and befit the modeſtie and civilitie of Women, and eſpecially the Virgin Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2195:3"/>Yea, ſuch things, which godly and learned men, well experienced in the holy Scriptures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of great knowledge and honeſt life, are wont to exerciſe and practiſe, not without a great deale of trouble, and much difficultie.</p>
            <p>We therefore deſiring and labouring by all meanes, in time to extirpate and roote out, all weeds and bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars out of the field of the holy Militant Church, haue Commanded and Charged our Reverend Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Aloyſius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tricariken,</hi> Ours and the Holy <hi>Apoſtolicall Chaires Nuntius</hi> in the Countryes of <hi>Lower-Germany,</hi> as alſo divers other Ordinaries, that they finding and perceiving the great dangers and ſcandalls which doe thence ariſe, ſhould (in the name of our <hi>Apoſtolicall Authoritie,</hi>) earneſtly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh, and forewarne, and exhort the aforeſaid Women and Maidens, to withdraw themſelues from ſuch intended courſes and practiſes, and to betake themſelues to better and wiſer wayes and devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <p>But whereas theſe preſumptuous Women, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning and deſpiſing the feare of God, and Vs, and abuſing the great reſpect due vnto the <hi>Apoſtolicall Sea,</hi> to the great prejudice of their owne ſoules, and offending of many good religious people, haue not onely not obeyed our Fatherly and Godly admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but haue not beene aſhamed to continue and goe on in theſe their idle practiſes, and to broach and produce many things contrary to the Godly Truth and Doctrine of the Church. We haue now earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolved to prevent ſuch a farther contempt and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2195:4"/>preſumption, with a ſharpe and bitter ſentence and penaltie. And to roote out and extirpate all ſuch plants and ſprouts vtterly, being ſo infectious, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious, and hurtfull to the Holy Church, for feare leaſt they ſpread themſelues farther, if they be not ſuppreſſed.</p>
            <p>Therefore having held wiſe and provident Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell with our Honourable Brothers, the Cardinalls of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Generall Inquiſitors, ſpecially de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted againſt all evill Hereſies of the ſaid Sea, with vnanimous Counſell and Conſent, according to the Decrees of the foreſaid Councells, adhering to the Inſtitutions of our Predeceſſors, Wee haue tituled the ſaid Convents and Congregations of the ſayd Women or Maidens, <hi>Shee-Ieſuites.</hi> And doomed their ſect and State, from the firſt beginning of their Inſtitution, by our <hi>Apoſtolicall Authoritie.</hi> And doe by the tenour of this preſent Edict of Ours, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the ſame to be voyde and of none effect or pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and that the ſame is of no worth, neither ever was.</p>
            <p>And becauſe they haue proceeded with the very action and execution of this their profeſſion, Wee doe by our <hi>Apoſtolicall Authoritie,</hi> vtterly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and annihilate the ſame, and make them ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to eternall abolition, and take away, and cut off the ſame from the moſt holy Church of God. Willing and ordaining, that the ſame Order of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Maidens, ſhall of all Chriſtian beleeving people, be held for ſuppreſſed and aboliſhed, extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, vtterly taken away, and extirpated. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2195:4"/>will Wee that the ſame Women or Maidens ſhall any wayes be tyed, or obliged to performe the ſolemne Vow which they ſo ſtrongly haue made to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, Wee will, ordaine, and declare, that all Shee-Viſiters, ſhee-regiſtrices, and ſhee-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voſts, as all other Shee-Governants and Officialls of the ſaid Congregation and ſect, by what name or title they may be named or called, ſhall by power of this our Edict be deprived of the Office, ſervice, or place which they haue taken vpon them to performe or execute.</p>
            <p>Wee doe likewiſe abſolue all and every Woman or Maiden, which vnder pretence of a ſolemne Vow, hath (vpon whatſoever occaſion in this kinde) bound or obliged her ſelfe to any obedience tending to this Order, and vtterly free them from ſuch Vow and Obligation. Yea even thoſe that haue in this nature tyed themſelues by approbation of an Oath.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, Wee doe ordaine, and command all Women or Maidens, and their afore-mentioned Governours, named or dignified with the foreſaid or other manner of titles, (by vertue of the holy obedience due vnto Vs, and vpon penaltie of our <hi>Bull,</hi> and farther Excommunication, which they will preſently incurre, and from the which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be abſolved by any but our ſelfe, and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall be <hi>Pope</hi> of this holy Citie of <hi>Rome</hi>) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and ſeperate themſelues from all thoſe Colled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or Houſes where they are aſſembled, prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2195:5"/>them to haue any more meetings or aſſemblies together, to conſult, conferre, or treate together, or performe either ſpirituall or temporall exerciſes. Willing and charging them preſently and ſpeedily to abandon and diſmiſſe the manner of habit ſuppoſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fally taken vpon them, and never to put on the ſame any more, neither to admit any other Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or Maidens to receiue and put on the ſame. As alſo that they with their conſent ſhall not ſuffer, nor counſell, helpe, or favour others to doe it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly, or in any manner whatſoever, neither ſhall they profeſſe themſelues, or make known themſelues to be religious perſons, followers of that pretended ſect and Congregation.</p>
            <p>For the better ſuppreſſing of which Aſſembly, Wee doe freely and willingly abſolue all thoſe Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Maidens, who haue really and punctually made their Vowes (as Wee ſaid before) with that intention, being in ſuch an eſtate, condemned and reprobated by the <hi>Apoſtolicall Chaire,</hi> although they haue not performed the promiſed conditions of their ſecret Vowes, nor could not performe the Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Vowes fully.</p>
            <p>But all thoſe who in any caſe haue made Vowes, (being they are ſimple Vowes to liue honeſtly and religiouſly, being ſeperated from the other, and this reprobate State, and the pretended ſect and Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, ſhunning and avoyding whatſoever hath by this Edict beene prohibited, theſe Wee permit to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelues to the obedience of the <hi>Ordinarie,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2195:5"/>with the vſe, but nor the full command of their Goods, but with ſuch power which Wee merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully graunt them, both in their liues, and before their deceaſe to diſpoſe of them to holy and pious vſes. Neuertheleſſe this prouided, that the ſame Goods ſhall, without any will or Teſtament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall, and be deriued vnto thoſe, which by right and equity were to ſucceede in them, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite the ſame, if ſo bee that theſe women or maidens had not made ſuch a vow of voluntary poverty.</p>
            <p>And in caſe any of theſe afore-ſayd women or mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens would betake themſelues to the eſtate of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony we graunt them free permiſſion to marrie: but with this proviſo, that they ſhall keepe that which therein is to bee obſerued, and we doe afford them our <hi>Apoſtollicall Benediction,</hi> and as farre as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity requires, the relaxation and quittance of all their vowes (as aforeſaid) made by them.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> teacheth, that hee that marries doth well, but hee that remaines vnmarried doth better, wee doe therefore, as earneſtly, and with as much power as wee can, admoniſh and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort thoſe afore-ſayd women and maidens, by the mercies of <hi>God,</hi> in our fatherly loue and care, that they would but recall and truely conſider, the zeale and affection which they haue had to embrace a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Religious, and Spirituall life, and to take vpon them the <hi>Lords</hi> yoke, and that they renounding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and all worldly luſes, cares, and concupiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2195:6"/>would betake themſelues into ſome holy and religious order inſtituted and approued of by this Holy <hi>Apoſtollicall Chaire.</hi> And there with a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, holy and godly deſire, and intentions, make their vowes vnto the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iacob:</hi> and with inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie of hands, and puritie and ſinceritie of heart, practizing and performing holy ſpirituall exerciſes of Religious workes, would manifeſt themſelues to bee the pureſt and pretiouſt part of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Sheepe and Flocke. And there kindle their lampes with the flames of Loue, and ſo prepare themſelues to meere the ſweete heauenly Bridegroome of their ſoules.</p>
            <p>Thus then wee doe ordaine, that theſe preſent Letters, and all the Contents of the ſame, yea not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, that the women or maidens of ſuch a Sect and Aſſembly, or any other, hauing ſome ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ſeruple of the Premiſes, or pretending to haue, ſhould not haue conſented vnto the ſame, or haue not beene ſummoned and heard in the matter. And that the reaſons of this ſame Edict, alleaged, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, and otherwiſe ſufficiently iuſtified, ſhall at no time whatſoever hereafter bee ſubiect to ſubreption, or obreption, nullitie, or invaliditie, or accounted wanting in our intentions. Or bee accuſed of any fault or defect, how great, vnthought of, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall the ſame might bee; neither bee leſſened or dimiſhed. No not although that in the afore-ſayd buſineſſe, the Solemnities, and all other things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayd, which ought to haue beene kept and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, were not proſecuted, obſerued, and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2195:6"/>Nor by reaſon of ſome Capitall point or Clauſe in Law, Ordinance, or Vſe, nor by reaſon of any totall breach or prejudice, nor vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or any other excuſe or cloake whatſoever: nor conclution of Law, nor any juſt reaſonable and and priuiledged reaſon, which for the ſtrength and validitie of the Premiſes, ought to haue beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced or performed. Yea although that of our afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd will and pleaſure, could no wayes nor no where appeare, nor bee made good or manifeſted other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife, yet the ſame ſhall not bee impugned, oppoſed, made invalidable, bee brought into Law, bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted, nor bee brought vpon termes of Law. Neither ſhall any eaſement, making of way, termes and times granted by Law, or any other Iudiciall acts and remedies of fauour, grace, or Iuſtice bee obtained, or any way granted in this behalfe. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall it bee lawfull for any one who hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſuch eaſements, to vſe or employ them, or benefit and helpe himſelfe with ſuch meanes in or without the Law. Neither ſhall theſe letters of ours bee comprehended vnder any other equall or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall fauours, which in time to come ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called, ſuſpended, held backe, or which might o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in time to come bee diſpoſed of: but theſe ſhall euer be excepted and exempted, and ſhall for euer hereafter ſtand firme and vnalterable, and haue their full force vigour and perfect effect. And ſhall bee obſerued and obeyed infringeable and vnvio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable, of all thoſe whom they doe concerne, or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2195:7"/>ſhall concerne hereafter. And thus (and no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) in this matter afore-ſayd ſhall it bee judged, by all Iudges, Ordinaries, Delegates, by the Auditors alſo of the affaires and matters concerning the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtollicall Palace,</hi> and the Cardinals of the holy <hi>Romiſh Church:</hi> Legates and the Nuntius, and all others of whatſoeuer authority or power they are or ſhall bee, in all Inſtances and Iudgements, depriuing them all of all authority and power of judging otherwiſe. Wherefore wee doe declare whatſoeuer ſhall be contrary, or bee attempted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this our fore-ſayd Edict and Letters, of whatſoeuer Authoritie the ſame may be found, to bee fruſtrate, quite voide, and of none effect, whether the ſame bee vndertaken wittingly or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, for the better execution of this our will and pleaſure, wee doe commaund by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtollicall</hi> Edict and Writing, all our Reuerend Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and well-beloued Sonnes, Ours, and the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtollicall Chaires</hi> Nuntius, all Patriarchs, Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours or Governours of the Church; Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, and Ordinaries, whereſoever they are ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; that as ſoone as our preſent letters ſhall come to them, or any of them, or ſhall any way be made knowne vnto them, ſolemnely to publiſh them, and cauſe them to bee publiſhed: and to put the ſame, and cauſe them to be put, in ſome place fit for that execution, either by themſelues or others, as they ſhall finde fit and expedient in the <hi>Lord.</hi> Alſo
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2195:7"/>Wee will and command them, earneſtly to ſenſure by ſentence, and ſeuerely to puniſh by Spirituall puniſhment, and other juſt and reaſonable meanes, which may conſtraine and compell them. All thoſe who are rebellious, gaine-ſaying, and will not obey our fore ſayd Edict, debarring them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving them from all manner and way of appeale, refuge, and recalling, employing to this end, the Temporall Magiſtrate, as farre as ſhall bee found requiſite and neceſſary. Notwithſtanding (as farre as ſhall be neceſſary) the Conſtitutions of <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight, our Predeceſſour, of bleſſed Memory, inſtituted one, and the Generall Counſell of two dayes Iourney, and all other contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>And to the end that this preſent Edict, and the Contents thereof may be made knowne and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to all men, and no man may pretend or plead ignorance, Wee likewiſe will and commaund, that the ſame, be by one, or diuers of our Couriers affixed and publiſhed vpon the Church doore of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran,</hi> and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> the Prince of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of this City, and of the <hi>Apoſtollicall Chaunceries.</hi> And vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Corner of the <hi>Flower-field.</hi> And when the Copies ſhall be taken off, re-printed, and diſtributed abroad, which be thus affixed and publiſhed, all thoſe (within two moneths after the day of the ſayd Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication) whom it doth concerne any way, ſhall ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be ſo tied and obliged, as if notice of the ſame were giuen to their owne perſons. Alſo that all the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2195:8"/>Copies thereof printed, being ſealed with the feale of any Perſon placed in Spirituall Dignity, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the hand of a <hi>Notarius Publicus,</hi> ſhall haue ſo much credence and beliefe given therevnto, as ought to be given vnto this preſent, if ſo be it were extended and ſhewed.</p>
            <p>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is not lawfull therefore for any one whoſoever, to tranſgreſſe theſe our Letter of Suppreſſion, annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſubjection, extenuation, and our <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Privation, Ablation, Obſolution, Remiſſion, and Our Commandement of Declaration, Permiſſion, Fauour or Grace, Admonition, Deſires, Will and Pleaſure; or to oppoſe the ſame, or contrarie the ſame, through bolde and impudent preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For whoſoever ſhall dare to vndertake and preſume ſo much, the ſame ſhall fall into the wrath and indignation of <hi>God Almightie,</hi> and of his holy <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given at Rome by Saint</hi> Peter, <date>
                     <hi>in the Yeare</hi> 1630. <hi>the thirteenth of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarie, and the eight Yeare of Our Papacie.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>E. Dat. A. Rondininus.</signed>
               <signed>Viewed and examined in the Councell.
<list>
                     <item>A. Durandus.</item>
                     <item>C. Montanus.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2195:8"/>
               <head>Regiſtred in the Secretarie of Roles.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the name of God, Amen.</hi> In the yeare of our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> 1930. the one and twentieth day of May, being the fourteenth Indiction, in the ninth yeare of the <hi>Papacie</hi> of the moſt <hi>Holy Father</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and our Lord <hi>Vrbanus</hi> the eight, by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of <hi>God, Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fore-ſayd Letters were publiſhed, and held at the Church doore of <hi>Lateran,</hi> and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> the Prince of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of this Citie, and of the <hi>Apoſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Chauncerie:</hi> and on the Corner of the <hi>Flower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field;</hi> As the manner is. By mee <hi>Auguſtine de Bolis Romane Courier</hi> of our moſt <hi>Holy Father</hi> the <hi>Pope.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mathias Spada Courier-maſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>F. Aertsb.</hi> of <hi>Comp. Nuntius.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
